# William Blair

GraalVM Oracle Labs Washington, D.C. U.S.A.

url: https://wdblair.io associations: ACM, IEEE google scholar

### **Current Position**

Senior Member of Technical Staff, Oracle Labs

## Research Interests

I am interested in developing novel program analysis techniques and defenses for cyber-security. I currently work on this topic on the GraalVM team within Oracle Labs. Previously, I explored how binary analysis tools can inform runtime monitors for cloud services. I had the opportunity to investigate this cloud security topic while interning in the Cyber Security Intelligence (CSI) team at IBM Research where I participated in the DARPA Cyber-Hunting at Scale (CHASE) program. I also use memory protection keys (MPKs) available in recent Intel CPUs to develop techniques to improve applications' memory safety, which is done as a part of the NSF Secure and Trustworthy Cyberspace (SaTC) Taming Memory Corruption with Security Monitors program.

Earlier in my PhD, I worked on *micro-fuzzing*, a novel fuzz testing technique to detect algorithmic complexity (AC) vulnerabilities in production Java programs and libraries. I evaluated the proposed micro-fuzzing technique with HotFuzz, a fuzz testing framework that detects AC vulnerabilities in Java libraries during the DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity (STAC) program. HotFuzz has detected previously unknown vulnerabilities in the Java Runtime Environment (JRE) that have been confirmed by Oracle and IBM. Furthermore, HotFuzz has found bugs in popular Java libraries, including org.json.

# Education

2014-2023 PhD in Computer Science, Boston University

Advisors: Manuel Egele, Hongwei Xi

2012-2014 MS in Computer Science, Boston University

Project: Dependent Types for Real Time Constraints

Advisor: Hongwei Xi

2008-2012 BA in Computer Science, Boston University

### **Publications**

- Mark Lemay, Qiancheng Fu, William Blair, Cheng Zhang, Hongwei Xi. A Dependently Typed Language with Dynamic Equality. In Proceedings of the ACM SIGPLAN International Workshop on Type-Driven Development (TyDE), Seattle, WA, US, September 2023.
- William Blair, William Robertson, Manuel Egele. ThreadLock: Native Principal Isolation Through Memory Protection Keys. In Proceedings of the ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communications Security (ASIACCS), Melbourne, VIC, Australia, July 2023.
- William Blair, William Robertson, Manuel Egele. MPKAlloc: Efficient Heap Meta-Data Integrity Through Hardware Memory Protection Keys. In Proceedings of the Conference on Detection of Intrusions and Malware & Vulnerability Assessment (DIMVA) Cagliari, Sardinia Italy, June 2022.
- William Blair, Andrea Mambretti, Sajjad Arshad, Michael Weissbacher, William Robertson, Engin Kirda, Manuel Egele. HotFuzz: Discovering Temporal and Spatial Denial-of-Service Vulnerabilities Through Guided Micro-Fuzzing. In the ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS) April 2022.
- Leila Delshadtehrani, Sadullah Canakci, William Blair, Manuel Egele, Ajay Joshi. FlexFilt: Towards Flexible Instruction Filtering for Security. In Proceedings of the Annual Computer Security Applications Conference (ACSAC) December 2021.
- William Blair, Andrea Mambretti, Sajjad Arshad, Michael Weissbacher, William Robertson, Engin Kirda, Manuel Egele. HotFuzz: Discovering Algorithmic Denial-of-Service Vulnerabilities Through Guided Micro-Fuzzing. In Proceedings of the ISOC Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS) San Diego, CA US, February 2020.
- William Blair, Hongwei Xi. Dependent Types for Multi-Rate Data Flows in Synchronous Programming. In Post-Proceedings of the ACM ML/OCAML Workshop September 2015.

## Patents

- Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Teryl Paul Taylor. Stateful Microservice-Aware Intrusion Detection. US Patent 11,720,667
- Frederico Araujo, Teryl Paul Taylor, Jiyong Jang, William Blair. Intrusion Detection in Micro-Services through Container Telemetry and Behavior Modeling. US Patent 11,748,473
- Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Sanjeev Das, Jiyong Jang. Guided Micro-Fuzzing through Hybrid Program Analysis. US Patent Application 17/444,497
- Frederico Araujo, William Blair, Teryl Paul Taylor. Automated Synthesis of Reference Policies for Runtime Microservice Protection. US Patent Application 17/390,881

# **Talks**

Symbolic Modeling of Micro Services for Intrusion Detection *IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy Poster Session 2021* 

Microservice-Aware Reference Monitoring through Hybrid Program Analysis 2021 FloCon 2021 at CMU Software Engineering Institute (SEI) HotFuzz: Finding Space and Time Vulnerabilities in Java Programs 2019 DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity P.I. Meeting Continuum: Finding Space and Time Vulnerabilities in Java Programs 2016 DARPA Space and Time Analysis for Cybersecurity P.I. Meeting Side Channels and Worst Case Behavior in Java 2016 Northeastern-WPI Seminar on Security Using a Portfolio of SMT Solvers in Software Development 2015 NEPLS Fall at Tufts University Dependent Types for Real Time Constraints 2015 ACM Sigplan ML Workshop at ICFP 2015 Integrating SMT into Software Development 2015 NEPLS Spring at Wesleyan University Debugging with Types in ATS 2014 Boston Haskell Meetup

### Service

2023	Session Chair for ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communications Security
2022	Sub-Reviewer for IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, IEEE European Symposium on
	Security and Privacy
2021	Trojan Horse Award reviewer for the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy
2021	Shadow Program Committee member for the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy
2021	Sub-Reviewer for NDSS, USENIX Security
2020	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY, DSN, USENIX Security
2019	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY
2018	Artifact Evaluation Committee member for ACSAC
2018	Sub-Reviewer for ACSAC, RAID, DIMVA, ACM CODASPY
2017	Artifact Evaluation Committee member for ACSAC
2017	Sub-Reviewer for ACM CODASPY

Sacricus Chair for ACM ASIA Conference on Computer and Communications Society

# Teaching

Spring 2021 TF for CS210 Computer Systems

Lectured on fundamentals of UNIX and C programming and helped students with their programming assignments. Over the course of the semester students implemented their own calculator that parsed and evaluated mathematical expressions given in infix notation. Their calculators used reverse polish notation (RPN) as an intermediate representation for simple arithmetic equations.

Fall 2020 TF for CS630 Graduate Design and Analysis of Algorithms

Lectured on topics including Linear Algebra, LUP Decomposition, Complexity, Approximation Algorithms, Randomized Algorithms, and Linear Programming. Managed a small

team of graders.

Spring 2015

TF for CS111 Introduction to Computer Science

Fall 2014

Assisted students through a breadth first introduction to Computer Science that covers programming in Functional, Imperative, and Object Oriented paradigms. Other topics such as Computer Organization, Assembly Programming, and Computational Complexity were briefly introduced as well. The class was adapted from the "CS For All" class developed at Harvey Mudd University. My role included leading discussion sections, grading, and holding office hours.

Spring 2014

TF for CS211 Object Oriented Programming

Assisted students with learning Objective C and writing applications for iOS devices. Students first built familiarity with the iOS environment by gradually constructing a tweeting App in iOS, and then developed their own original apps.

#### Awards

IBM Invention Plateau Award
IBM First Patent Application Award
3rd Place speaker at 7th Annual BU CISE Graduate Student Workshop (CGSW 7.0)
2019 2nd Place speaker at 6th Annual BU CISE Graduate Student Workshop (CGSW 6.0)

2018 Student Travel Award to the IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy

2016 Sixth Summer School on Formal Techniques at Menlo College

Verification Mentoring Workshop at the International Conference on Computer Aided

Verification (CAV)

# **Professional Experience**

2023-present

Senior Member of Technical Staff at Oracle Labs

Investigating language-based security topics within the GraalVM.

2019-2021

Research Intern at IBM Research, Thomas J. Watson Research Center

Investigated topics related to Intrusion Detection in Microservices with the Cyber Security

Intelligence (CSI) team.

2015 *Soft* 

Software Engineer Intern at ViaSat

Assisted in developing a business process engine (BPE) that provides a fault tolerant programming framework for executing and managing workflows across distributed systems.

2013

Software Engineer Intern at ViaSat

Investigated how mobile applications received multi-media from content providers by reverse engineering native ARM libraries in Android applications, and using a man-in-the-middle server to augment Javascript applications.

2009-2012

Software Engineer at 829 Studios LLC

Designed, implemented, and deployed OfferedLocal, a web application that allows businesses to run location based advertising campaigns across social networks like Facebook and Twitter. The start-up participated in Mass Challenge and was featured in the Demo Fall 2011 Conference.

Developed and maintained the back office system for the Licensing Industry Merchandisers Association (LIMA), along with an online directory of member companies.

2009-2010 Technician at BU Electronics Design Facility

Developed firmware for a medical prototype as part of the Fluorescence-Assisted Resection and Exploration (FLARE) project at Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center. The system allowed an external device to control the power output of lasers and regulated their temperature using Peltier coolers. The firmware featured serial communication, analog to digital controllers (ADC) to measure laser temperature, and proportional integral and derivative (PID) controllers to control the Peltier coolers' temperature via pulse width modulation. Assisted in the design, layout, and testing of circuit boards for Physics experiments, including the Compact Muon Solenoid (CMS) experiment at CERN.